<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<help>
  <menu title="Instructions">
    <item title="Introduction to Secret Letter">
      <paragraph>[italic type]Nightfall[roman type] takes place in a city the Player Character knows well; he's lived there all his life and so has a far better knowledge of the local geography than the player begins with. To help bridge this knowledge gap you can use the command GO TO X or FIND X (these mean the same thing) to go either to a named destination or an object the player knows about. This command will take the player character towards his destination one step at a time. To continue towards the destination, use the CONTINUE command (which you can abbreviate to C). Note that the CONTINUE command can be used after any number of intervening commands, including explicit compass-movement commands.</paragraph>
      <paragraph>The exit lister on the top of the right page shows a list of directions you can go in from your current location. Any directions in upper case indicate directions to locations you haven't yet visited.</paragraph>
      <paragraph>Several locations trigger memories the first time you visit them. If you want see the memory associated with the location you're in again, you can use the command REMEMBER. To see the memory associated with another location you've visited, use the command REMEMBER {location Name}, for example REMEMBER BAR. You can use the command PLACES to list the names of all the places you've visited. To recapitulate all the memories you've triggered so far, you can use the command RECAP.</paragraph>
      <paragraph>You can use the command THINK to get some ideas for what to do next. These will be the player character's ideas, and some of them may be better than others. This command helps bridge the gap between player knowledge and player character knowledge. If you're stuck and THINK doesn't give you enough of a hint, you can try the command THINK HARDER (or just THINK HARD), which in some cases may provide a much more explicit hint.</paragraph>
      <paragraph>In brief, make regular use of the THINK command as an integral part of the game. Use THINK HARDER for hints.</paragraph>
      <paragraph>To converse with other characters use commands like ASK BOB ABOUT RING or TELL BOB ABOUT DAGGER; these commands may be abbreviated to A RING or T DAGGER. You can also respond to certain questions asked by other characters with a simple YES or NO.</paragraph>
      <paragraph>Finally, you may not like the ending you get first time round. To avoid having to play all the way through again from the beginning to find a better ending, you may want to save at fairly regular intervals.</paragraph>
    </item>
    <item title="Instructions for Play">
      <menu title="Instructions for Play">
        <item title="About Interactive Fiction">
          <paragraph>The game you are playing is a work of Interactive Fiction.  In interactive fiction you play the main character of a story.  You type commands which determine the actions of the character and the flow of the plot.  Some IF games include graphics, but most do not: the imagery is provided courtesy of your imagination.  On the other hand, there's a wide range of action available: whereas in other games you may be restricted to shooting, movement, or searching items you can click on with a mouse, IF allows you a wide range of verbs.</paragraph>
        </item>
        <item title="What to do with &gt;">
          <paragraph>The &gt; sign is where the game says, "Okay, what do you want to do now?"  You may respond by typing an instruction -- usually an imperative verb, possibly followed by prepositions and objects.  So, for instance, LOOK, LOOK AT FISH, TAKE FISH.</paragraph>
        </item>
        <item title="Getting Started">
          <paragraph>The first thing you want to do when starting a game is acquaint yourself with your surroundings and get a sense of your goal. To this end, you should read the introductory text carefully. Sometimes it contains clues. You will also want to look at the room you are in. Notice where the exits from the room are, and what objects are described here. If any of these seem interesting, you may want to EXAMINE them.</paragraph>
          <paragraph>You might also want to examine yourself (EXAMINE ME) to see whether the author has left you any clues about your character. TAKE INVENTORY will tell you what you're carrying, as well.</paragraph>
          <paragraph>Once you've gotten your bearings, you may want to explore. Move from room to room, and check out every location available.</paragraph>
        </item>
        <item title="Rooms and Travel">
          <paragraph>At any given time, you are in a specific location, or room. When you go into a room, the game will print a description of what you can see there. This description will contain two vital kinds of information: things in the room you can interact with or take, and a list of exits, or ways out. If you want to see the description again, you may just type LOOK.</paragraph>
          <paragraph>When you want to leave a location and go to another one, you may communicate this to the game using compass directions: eg, GO NORTH. For simplicity's sake, you are allowed to omit the word GO, and to abbreviate the compass directions. So you may use NORTH, SOUTH, EAST, WEST, NORTHEAST, SOUTHEAST, NORTHWEST, SOUTHWEST, UP, and DOWN, or in short form N, S, E, W, NE, SE, NW, SW, U, and D.</paragraph>
          <paragraph>In some locations, IN and OUT will also be useful.</paragraph>
        </item>
        <item title="Objects">
          <paragraph>Throughout the game there will be assorted objects that you can do things with. Most importantly, you may TAKE or GET items, and (when you are tired of them) DROP them again. INVENTORY (abbreviated I) will list the items you are currently holding.</paragraph>
          <paragraph>There are usually assorted things you may do with these objects. OPEN, CLOSE, WEAR, EAT, LOCK, and UNLOCK are especially common.</paragraph>
          <paragraph>Occasionally, you will find that the game does not recognize the name of an object even though it has been described as being in the room with you. If this is the case, the object is just there for scenery, and you may assume that you do not need to interact with it.</paragraph>
        </item>
        <item title="Controlling the Game">
          <paragraph>
            There are a few simple commands for controlling the game itself. These are:[linebreak]
            [indent]
            SAVE saves a snapshot of the game as it is now.[linebreak]
            [indent]
            RESTORE puts the game back to a previous saved state. You may keep as many saved games as you like.[linebreak]
            [indent]
            RESTART puts the game back to the way it was at the beginning.[linebreak]
            [indent]QUIT ends the game.
          </paragraph>
        </item>
        <item title="How the World is Assembled">
          <menu title="How the World is Assembled">
            <item title="Space">
              <paragraph>Most IF games are set in a world made up of rooms without internal division. Movement between rooms is possible; movement within a room does not always amount to anything. >WALK OVER TO THE DESK is rarely a useful sort of command. On the other hand, if something is described as being high or out of reach, it is sometimes relevant to stand on an object to increase your height. This kind of activity tends to be important only if prompted by the game text.</paragraph>
            </item>
            <item title="Containment">
              <paragraph>One thing that IF does tend to model thoroughly is containment. Is something in or on something else? The game keeps track of this, and many puzzles have to do with where things are -- in the player's possession, lying on the floor of the room, on a table, in a box, etc.</paragraph>
            </item>
            <item title="Types of Action">
              <paragraph>Most of the actions you can perform in the world of IF are brief and specific. &gt;WALK WEST or &gt;OPEN DOOR are likely to be provided. &gt;TAKE A JOURNEY or &gt;BUILD A TABLE are not. Things like &gt;GO TO THE HOTEL are on the borderline: some games allow them, but most do not. In general, abstract, multi-stage behavior usually has to be broken down in order for the game to understand it.</paragraph>
            </item>
            <item title="Other Characters">
              <paragraph>Other characters in IF games are sometimes rather limited. On the other hand, there are also games in which character interaction is the main point of the game. You should be able to get a feel early on for the characters -- if they seem to respond to a lot of questions, remember what they're told, move around on their own, etc., then they may be fairly important. If they have a lot of stock responses and don't seem to have been the game designer's main concern, then they are most likely present either as local color or to provide the solution to a specific puzzle or set of puzzles. Characters in very puzzle-oriented games often have to be bribed, threatened, or cajoled into doing something that the player cannot do -- giving up a piece of information or an object, reaching something high, allowing the player into a restricted area, and so on.</paragraph>
            </item>
          </menu>
        </item>
        <item title="If You Get Stuck">
          <menu title="if You Get Stuck">
            <item title="Explore">
              <paragraph>Examine every object and look at everything in your inventory. Open all the doors you can find, and go through them. Look inside all closed containers. Make sure you've exhausted all the options in your environment.</paragraph>
              <paragraph>Try out all your senses. If the game mentions texture, odor, or sound, try touching, smelling, listening to, or tasting objects.</paragraph>
              <paragraph>Be thorough. If you still can't figure out what to do, try opening windows, looking under beds, etc. Sometimes objects are well-hidden.</paragraph>
            </item>
            <item title="Read carefully">
              <paragraph>Reread. Look back at things you've already looked at. Sometimes this will trigger an idea you hadn't thought of.</paragraph>
              <paragraph>Take hints from the prose of the game. Things that are described in great detail are probably more important than things that are given one-liners. Play with those objects. If a machine is described as having component parts, look at the parts, and try manipulating them.  Likewise, notice the verbs that the game itself uses. Try using those yourself. Games often include special verbs -- the names of magic spells, or other special commands. There's no harm in attempting something if the game mentions it.</paragraph>
              <paragraph>Check the whole screen. Are there extra windows besides the main window?  What's going on in those?  Check out the status bar, if there is one -- it may contain the name of the room you're in, your score, the time of day, your character's state of health, or some other important information.  If there's something up there, it's worth paying attention to that, too.  When and where does it change?  Why is it significant?  If the bar is describing your character's health, you can bet there is probably a point at which that will be important.</paragraph>
            </item>
            <item title="Be creative">
              <paragraph>Rephrase. If there's something you want to do, but the game doesn't seem to understand you, try alternative wordings.</paragraph>
              <paragraph>Try variations. Sometimes an action doesn't work, but does produce some kind of unusual result. These are often indications that you're on the right track, even if you haven't figured out quite the right approach yet. Pressing the red button alone may only cause a grinding noise from inside the wall, so perhaps pressing the blue and then the red will open the secret door.</paragraph>
              <paragraph>Consider the genre of the game. Mysteries, romances, and thrillers all have their own types of action and motivation. What are you trying to do, and how do conventional characters go about doing that? What's the right sort of behavior for a detective/romance heroine/spy?</paragraph>
            </item>
            <item title="Cooperate">
              <paragraph>Play with someone else. Two heads are often better than one. If that doesn't work, try emailing the author or (better yet) posting a request for hints on the newsgroup rec.games.int-fiction.  For best results, put the name of the game you want help with in the subject line; then leave a page or so of blank spoiler space (so that no one will read about where you got to in the game unless they've already played it), and describe your problem as clearly as possible.  Someone will probably be able to tell you how to get around it.</paragraph>
            </item>
          </menu>
        </item>
      </menu>
    </item>
    <item title="Time and Turns">
      <menu title="Time and Turns">
        <item title="General">
          <paragraph>The top of the right page shows the time of day (i.e. the current time within the story world of the game). You don't have forever to resolve the situation you're in, and if you run out of time you'll reach a losing ending.</paragraph>
          <paragraph>In a standard Inform game, time advances at one minute per turn. In this game, some actions take less than a minute: some of these take no time at all, and some take some fraction of a minute. Actions that typically take only a few seconds include examining unimportant objects and basic inventory manipulation like taking and dropping thngs. This allows you more turns before you finally run out of time. Note that other actions, like moving from place to place, or examining more complex objects (like reading a book), typically take a full minute still. The result is a very rough approximation to realism in these timings.</paragraph>
          <paragraph>In game play terms, this means that you may or may not see the game time (shown on the top of the right page) advance on any particular term. This doesn't necessarily mean the turn took no time; it may mean it took some length of time less than 60 seconds (so that if you repeated the same action several times you'd eventually see the time advance). If you like, you can change the way the current time is displayed so that it shows seconds as well as hours and minutes. This will make it clear precisely how long each action is taking, but you may find that attending to such precise game mechanics detracts from engagement with the story.</paragraph>
          <paragraph>You can use the commands SHOW SECONDS and HIDE SECONDS to add or remove the seconds element from the time displayed on the top of the right page.</paragraph>
          <paragraph>Note that since there are a variable number of turns per minutes, you can't work out how many turns you've taken simply from the game time. If for any reason you do want to know this, you can use the TURNS command.</paragraph>
        </item>
        <item title="Time Limit Hint (spoiler)">The game takes place entirely at night, so the very latest it can end is just before dawn, around 4:30 am.</item>
      </menu>
    </item>
    <item title="Hints">
      <paragraph>Nightfall is a semi-puzzleless game. There are a few puzzles, but they are not meant to be particularly challenging and they are not the main point of the game. The main point is to work out what's going on and what to do about it. Several endings are possible, depending on how things play out.</paragraph>
      <paragraph>Don't be in too much of a hurry to rush through the city; take time to read the text, it may be important. In particular, certain locations trigger memories the first time you visit them, and the back-story formed by these memories is important. If you want to see the memory associated with the location you're in again, you can use the command REMEMBER. To see the memory associated with another location you've visited, use the command REMEMBER &lt;location name&gt;, for example REMEMBER BAR. You can use the command PLACES to list the names of all the places you've visited. To recapitulate all the memories you've triggered so far, you can use the command RECAP.</paragraph>
      <paragraph>Nightfall has several possible endings, which broadly fall into three main types. It's not possible to put the game into a state where you can't reach one of the endings, but it's certainly possible to put it into a state where you can't reach one of the better endings, so if you think you may want to see more than one ending, it's probably a good idea to save quite often.</paragraph>
      <paragraph>The individual puzzles in Nightfall aren't meant to be particularly difficult, but if you do get stuck, try using the THINK command, which will offer some suggestions based on the player character's knowledge. If that doesn't give you enough help, you can try the command THINK HARDER which may give you rather more explicit hints. THINK HARDER is in effect a hints command; using it more than once may give you increasingly explicit hints. You can safely use the THINK command without getting spoilers; use THINK HARDER if you want hints.</paragraph>
      <paragraph>The meta-puzzle in Nightfall is clued partly by the various recollections triggered by various locations and by what's written on certain things. To refresh your memory of these you can use the RECAP command.</paragraph>
    </item>
    <item title="Credits">
      <paragraph>Nightfall by Eric Eve.</paragraph>
      <paragraph>Inform 7 by Graham Nelson, with several useful extensions by Emily Short.</paragraph>
      <paragraph>Alpha-testing by Jim Aikin, Michel Nizette, and El Clerigo Urbatain.</paragraph>
      <paragraph>Beta-testing by: Rune Berg, Stefano Bonora, Jason Catena, Danii, D.J. Hastings, Carl Muckenhoupt, Michel Nizette, S. John Ross, Dirk Straube, Mike Tarbert, El Clerigo Urbatain and Jerome West.</paragraph>
      <paragraph>Special thanks to all these testers who between them uncovered a multitude of issues and offered a host of suggestions to make this game far better than it otherwise would have been.</paragraph>
      <paragraph>This version of Nightfall is freely hosted by Textfyre, Inc and implemented by Thomas Lynge of Tenteo Consulting.</paragraph>
    </item>
  </menu>
</help>
